<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title></title>
  <subtitle>Offering a range of Holistic options for your animals. All our sessions move at your animal&#39;s own pace - with empathy, kindness and respect for your animal.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://holistichoundaoanimals.co.uk/feed/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href=""/>
  <updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id></id>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Self-selection (Zoopharmacognosy)</title>
    <link href="/services/self-selection/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/self-selection/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is animal herbal self-selection?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wild animals naturally forage and have been observed seeking out and selecting substances on which to self-medicate. This can be the selection of not only plants and foliage, but also minerals, which can be found in soils and clays. On taking up substances and/or plant constituents this could relieve their issue or address an imbalance in their body. This is known as zoopharmacognosy, and this method of self-selection also applies to, and is observed in, domesticated animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A herbal self-selection session offers support for animals for a range of issues, including emotional and behavioural, as well as physical concerns such as inflammatory issues which could affect joints, stomach etc. Additionally skin, eye, ear, respiratory and immune issues, to name a few, could also benefit. Alternatively a range of detox or mineral rich products could be offered for selection if you feel your animal has no specific issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However where an issue is present that you contacted us about, animals do not always select herbs and oils initially to support this. At the consultation you will be given information about this and the self-selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to see what other professionals make of zoopharmacognosy, just click the link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dogsfirst.ie/zoopharmacognosy-demonstrated-on-me/&quot;&gt;A Zoopharmacognosy Experiment: Dogs First - Dr Conor Brady&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does the session involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the session we request completion of a Consultation form, and ask that you contact your vet to ensure they are willing for the session to go ahead - if your vet requires further information we are happy to communicate directly with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on our knowledge and experience, we prepare an outline plan of herbal options taking into account all the information supplied by yourselves about your animal. However, as the process is guided by your animal, this plan is very fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the self-selection session a range of dried herbs, hydrosols and gentle essential oils, along with a range of seasonally foraged plant materials, are offered to your animal in sequence. The session can take around 1½ - 2 hours from start to finish and would be best arranged at a time when there will be no interruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this the body language and behaviour of the animal is observed to see whether or not they are interested in the product choices offered. If interested the animal may eat, smell or even have them applied topically, or roll in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advice and support will be given on how best for you to offer or apply any products that have been selected by your animal in order to maintain their future well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/self-selection/essential-oils.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bottle of essential oils&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use of essential oils for self-selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are Essential oils?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essential oils are generally extracted through the process of steam distillation from plant matter such as bark, flowers, fruit, leaves and roots. During the process steam passes through the plant matter breaking up the micro particles of the plant separating out the volatile (essential oil), from the non-volatile (hydrolat or hydrosols) elements. The (essential) oils are then collected as they accumulate on the surface. The water based hydrosols contain natural constituents but in a more diluted form. Other forms of extraction include CO2 and solvent extraction (absolutes), and expression or cold-pressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is wide variation in shelf life of essential oils which is linked to their constituents, with citrus and pine essential oils having a shorter shelf life. Essential oils should be checked reglarly for oxidation, which can affect smell, viscosity and appearance (cloudy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concentrated essential oils contain the characteristic odour and chemical constituents of the plants, such as phenols, monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes. The concentration of these constituents will vary depending on the essential oil. We are aware of essential oil sensitivities in cats and tailor our sessions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering essential oils to animals allows them to have access to, and to self-select, constituents they may not have contact with in their domestic setting. Many essential oils have calming and relaxing properties, thus potentially reducing stress levels, which in turn supports and promotes physical well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Does aromatherapy affect animals?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an essential oil is inhaled between 30 - 70% (on average 50%) of chemical constituents within the oil are absorbed via mucous linings of the respiratory pathways into the bloodstream, and ultimately into the brain by crossing the Blood Brain Barrier. Inhalation could therefore be beneficial for both emotional issues (such as anxiety, depression) and respiratory issues as they have a more immediate effect. Oils with analgesic or sedative effects will also have a faster reaction time and stronger effect with neurotransmitters sending messages to the affected areas (ie, reduce pain, sedate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The olfactory system, or sense of smell, is linked to the limbic system of the brain which deals with, amongst other things, memory and emotions, and as such some odours may trigger an emotional response. Inhalation of supportive essential oils could release memories and thus restore balance and well being, as ultimately the emotional state affects the physical state. Essential oils are therefore supportive for a range of emotional, behavioural and physical issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We only use essential oils that are ethically sourced and from companies that guarantee their purity. We would recommend applying this criteria if looking to purchase oils for use in the home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using diffusers around animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several types of diffusers on the market and the amount, and frequency, of essential oil that is dispersed into the environment varies with each of these. The two main methods of dispersing the essential oils are by using a nebulising diffuser, or an ultrasonic diffuser. The nebulising diffuser disperses the essential oil into the air in a fine spray and thus the oil is still in its concentrated form. The ultrasonic diffuser again disperses a fine mist, but the difference is water is dispersed along with the essential oil and this therefore dilutes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If using a diffuser with essential oils in the home your animal should not be left unattended. Only use for a limited amount of time (to ensure no build-up of vapours); with ventilation and the ability for your animal to leave the room at any and all times, being necessities too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their behaviour should also be monitored whilst in the vicinity of a diffuser as they will indicate whether they like or dislike the oil - more information regarding this can be discussed at a self-selection session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cats, however, lack certain liver enzymes which assist in the metabolism of many essential oil constituents - &amp;quot; ... cats are quite susceptible to toxicity from nutmeg oil and tea tree oil. But, a small amount of any essential oil, and a moderate amount of most, will not harm your cat.&amp;quot; (Tisserand Institute).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless essential oils that contain phenols are best avoided around cats (particularly wintergreen, anise, birch, basil, fennel, thyme, clove, and oregano) which contain higher levels (50%+).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Self-selection (Zoopharmacognosy) Session prices:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cat session - £30.00, Dog session - £35.00, Horse session - £40.00&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mileage up to a 20 mile radius from my base is included in the price, along with all products offered and left after the session.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to arrange a session, or you have any questions or concerns, &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;please get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfPtGFTjw3sMIDt8PDQWafJGqct56lcLkhwk7YZ__0xPBNkRA/viewform&quot;&gt;Link to the Consultation Form which requires completion prior to the session.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An information sheet with further guidance on arranging and preparing for the session will also be made available at the session booking.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bach® Flower Remedies</title>
    <link href="/services/bach-flower-remedies/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/bach-flower-remedies/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Supporting your animal with Bach® Flower Remedies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Edward Bach took what was probably seen as an unorthodox approach in his field of medicine, in that he felt the emotional state had an impact on health, and that emotions such as fear and unhappiness could lead to ill-health. Thus by addressing emotional imbalance it would halt progression to physical health problems. The 38 remedies were borne out of this belief and Dr Bach devoted his life to creating these, and also established The Bach® Centre in Oxfordshire. This statement from Nelsons® (who are partnered with the Bach® Centre, and prepare their essences) really resonates -
“Bach® Original Flower Remedies was founded on the simple idea that ingredients born from nature can be incredibly powerful in supporting our emotional wellbeing ….”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelsons is the only company authorised by The Bach® Centre to produce the Bach® flower essences - created by using wild flowers, trees and bushes, some of which are still hand-picked from gardens at The Bach® Centre. Flower essences are prepared by using both the sun method (using only sunlight and fresh spring water) and boiling method (simmering in fresh spring water using an enamel pan). The resulting energised water, and filtered water, are then traditionally preserved with brandy, thus creating the mother tincture - 2 drops of this are then used to prepare stock bottles. Flower essences work on a vibrational level, containing the vibrational energy of flowers and plants, and as such do not interfere with medication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These remedies are able to support current emotional disturbances in animals, birds and reptiles as they are responsive to the Bach® flower essences, with many anecdotal and success stories to support this. Rescue Remedy® , which combines five Bach® Original Flower Essences, is well known among animal carers, and is often available in pet first aid kits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does the session involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the session we request completion of a Consultation form, and ask that you contact your vet to ensure they are willing for the session to go ahead - if your vet requires further information we are happy to communicate directly with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Bach® Flower Remedies session we meet both you and your animal, and after discussion and observations we combine a small number of the essences taking into account their detailed history, both past and present. We also offer this service as a remote session via Zoom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session lasts around 30 - 45 minutes, with preparation of a remedy bottle, and instructions for use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note we use only flower essences with no alcohol content.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bach® Flower Remedies Session price:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Animal session - £25.00&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mileage up to a 20 mile radius from my base is included in the price.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to arrange a session, or you have any questions or concerns, &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;please get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScPVpjjkPhLHCe9rczJUpoXZE4wWQiod0EMNBXUvg4ClUPv5Q/viewform&quot;&gt;Link to the Consultation form which requires completion prior to the session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reiki (Energy Healing)</title>
    <link href="/services/reiki-energy-healing/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/reiki-energy-healing/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is Reiki?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reiki is a form of energy healing that works holistically, and is a non-invasive therapy that provides natural healing vibrations. This energy is transferred or transmitted to the animal through the hands of a practitioner, by either hands-on, by distance or by absent (where the animal is not present). This then flows to the area it is needed most; assisting the animal in its natural healing process by releasing emotional blocks and balancing energies. This in turn could promote relaxation which could have a positive impact on some behavioural issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reiki could also help:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aid recovery from an illness, surgery or injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relieve stress, calm anxious and nervous animals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise energy levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relieve aches and pains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reiki should always be given with love, and a calmness of mind, to open up the communication channels. It can be both an emotional and spiritual experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When animals are open to receiving Reiki they are very sensitive to the healing energy. During the session itself they may enter a deeply relaxed and peaceful state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does the session involve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the session we request completion of a Consultation form, as well as requesting you advise your vet about the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the session Reiki can be given by either hands-on (by placing hands on the animal), or by distance (where hands are placed at a short distance away from the animal).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An animal will indicate their preference as to how (hands-on or distance), and if they wish, to receive Reiki, and when they wish a session to conclude - thus all guided by the animal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session lasts on average around 30 - 45 minutes from start to finish and would be best arranged at a time when there will be no interruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reiki (Energy Healing) Session price&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Animal session - £20.00&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mileage up to a 20 mile radius from my base is included in the price.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to arrange a session, or you have any questions or concerns, &lt;a href=&quot;/contact/&quot;&gt;please get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSciLS16DkBjmNd6DiIs9b3iR6-vsxsW27JxiCsxDYKeToTYeQ/viewform&quot;&gt;Link to the Consultation Form which requires completion prior to the session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An information sheet with further guidance on arranging and preparing for the session will also be made available at the session booking.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Enrichment</title>
    <link href="/services/enrichment/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/enrichment/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is Enrichment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The act or process of adding or improving the quality or power of something by adding something else”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So how can we translate this to animals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can add species appropriate items to their environment to stimulate senses and behaviour, along with offering and giving your animal the ability to choose. The European Commission has a document that requires “provision of enrichment materials to pigs” and states should provide “a sufficient quantity of suitable materials necessary to enable pigs to fulfil their innate needs to look for food (edible materials), bite (chewable materials), root (investigable materials) and manipulate (manipulable materials)”. This may be due to research finding that enrichment reduced the rate of aggression amongst pigs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we think about our daily routine with our animals we have a huge impact on their decisions, which is needed to keep them safe and often to be able to fit into our daily lives. But what makes your animal “tick”; what do they enjoy? Enrichment should bring enjoyment to your animal, positive experiences, and bring the wider world into their environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Could this benefit your animal?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By introducing new experiences to your animal and giving them options to make decisions you not only build a better understanding of them, but it also enhances your bond. Problem solving is also well documented across a range of species and birds, in particular crows are remarkable problem solvers. Problem solving and enrichment is often cited as resulting in calmer, more confident animals, particularly in new situations, and an increase in optimism. Curiosity has also been shown as a key driver for learning. Link to OpenLearn information about problem-solving in animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/enrichment/horse-field.webp&quot; alt=&quot;horses in field&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Providing enrichment for equines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different terrain for horses and donkeys, such as sloping or hilly areas, and the introduction of obstacles such as felled logs and uneven surfaces could make use of different muscle groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to woodland and rough grazing, a sand-filled area or pond could also provide enrichment within the field or track setting, whilst also encouraging movement. Scratching posts can be made from broom brushes and are well received by horses, especially if access to suitable substitutes like trees is limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horses and donkeys will naturally browse on (hedgerow) plants such as cow parsley, nettles, etc, as well as overhanging tree branches and shrubs, and access to these could be beneficial to your horse, as well as natural enrichment. If available this would typically make up around 10% of their diet, but can be as high as 50% in some cases. The greater diversity of plants available will allow your horse access to, and the ability to select from, the many constituents these plants offer, and the amount your horse requires to maintain their health and well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/enrichment/dog-chewing.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;dog using enrichment mat to find food&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enrichment for companion animals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enrichment can be made accessible within the confines of a garden or yard, or room in a house, and can take many forms. Knowing your animal is the key to providing this for them; basically what makes them happy. For your dog this could be as simple as placing their favourite toy in a pile of autumn leaves and giving them guidance to seek it out - seeking games, along with a variety of problem solving games, supports mental development and boosts confidence. As dogs see the colours yellow and blue predominantly, these could also be incorporated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogs are also driven by scent, creating a picture of their environment by using this tool, and can be added for enrichment. While out on a walk with your dog, be present with them - what do you hear and smell; observe them and see what interests them, do they sniff certain objects, for example a feather. Overgrown grassy areas hide a multitude of scents, particularly small animals that may frequent the area. When you can, let your dog choose which path to take, even for part of your walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your garden - if your dog loves digging, are you able to turn over an area for them to do this? Do they love digging in the sand when you are out and about? Could you add a sandpit to their environment, that can be covered when not in use? Does your dog love swimming? On a recent holiday we took a paddle-board and our dog loved swimming out to us and then riding on it while we were in the sea. Could you introduce water, even a paddling pool, to their area? Dogs and cats would benefit from the introduction of structures at varying heights, creating an observational point for them, as well as working different muscle groups when accessing them. In addition a &amp;quot;den&amp;quot; area could provide a &amp;quot;chill out zone&amp;quot; or area of shade in hotter weather, or just somewhere to play hide and seek. Many cats and dogs enjoy fresh plants and also dried herbs and may roll in these, or just inhale the aroma. Cats could make use of a log as a scratching post, or a bigger wood structure to allow them to climb naturally. Even a couple of old wooden stepladders, with secured planks across from one to the other, would create an interesting structure for cats. A range of plants could also be introduced - for more information see our Sensory Garden page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cats love high places, and there are many wonderful structures that can be bought to allow them to move around your room off the ground when in the house or in a catio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/enrichment/sniff-dog.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;dog sniffing scent on plant&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scents &amp;amp; Sniffing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dog Field Study found sniffing has a direct impact on a dog&#39;s pulse rate. By giving your dog time to sniff while out on a walk it can reduce their pulse rate, with more intense sniffing reducing it further. By adding length to their lead this increases the amount of time your dog will spend sniffing, with a dog off lead spending the most. Statistics from the study state dogs on a long lead (5 metres) spend 280% more time sniffing when compared to a short lead (1.5 metres); with 330% more time sniffing when off lead. When your dog becomes calm and relaxed this impacts their heart rate by reducing it, and consequently their pulse rate. Thus slowing down and stopping during your walk would allow your dog to sniff, and by varying walks and taking your dog to new locations this will also provide environmental enrichment for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scent makes up a large part of a dog’s sensory world; building confidence and coping skills as more understanding is gained. Time spent analysing odours lowers the pulse, as raised above, and could also promote cognitive function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your dog builds up a picture of its environment by sniffing and Alexandra Horowitz writes &amp;quot;As we see the world, the dog smells it ..... The world of scent is at least as rich as the world of sight&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To maintain and support the lining of your dog&#39;s nose Vitamin A will certainly be beneficial and can be found in a number of foods, including herbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As sniffing is mentally stimulating for your dog, allowing your dog a period of “down-time” after a lot of sniffing interaction would be very beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/enrichment/cat-licking.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;cat licking&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Licking &amp;amp; Chewing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licking and chewing are soothing in their actions for dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Licking has been cited as promoting relaxation for dogs and cats, due particularly to the release of endorphins (feel-good chemicals) and often LickiMats are useful in a variety of situations. Consequently, stressful situations may trigger excessive licking and grooming, though not exclusively, and other causes should be ruled out by your vet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chewing also has a calming effect for dogs, releasing Serotonin and Dopamine, giving dogs a tool to “self-medicate” when anxious or stressed, and hard chews such as antler, or yak chews may be beneficial, though you should always consider how your dog would interact and and whether these would be appropriate for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chewing may also be useful for cats too, particularly supporting good dental health, and silver vine sticks may be beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stress and tension can be carried through the jaws and shoulders of dogs, and should you encounter this it may be beneficial to offer a soft chew initially to relax the muscles, after which a harder chew could be offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Holistichoundaoa&quot;&gt;Check our available enrichment products via our shop on Etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sensory Gardens</title>
    <link href="/services/sensory-gardens/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/sensory-gardens/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is a sensory garden?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are areas that are designed to have a variety of elements that usually stimulate a range of senses, but could be designed to target just one or two, such as smell and taste. This could be provided for animals by planting a variety of herbs and plants they could interact with. For more information on suitable plants see below, or why not arrange a Herbal Choices session to identify which plants are of particular interest. If using containers, care should be taken in choosing those that do not leach chemicals; this also includes the use of worn tyres which also have the potential to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stimulate other senses, such as touch, other elements could be added including a variety of materials to walk on such as pebbles, mulch, twigs, sand, wooded and gravelled areas. A water feature such as a pond or stream could also be beneficial, and sound could be introducted by adding fountains or waterfalls, or grasses that would create sound when they move in the wind; however adding objects that create loud or unpredictable noises are best avoided. Some animals may also enjoy things such as wind chimes, but you will be best gauged if this is suitable for their character. Lawned areas, or chamomile lawn, that are maintained pesticide-free, however small, are encouraged rather than &amp;quot;plastic&amp;quot; or artificial grass which can heat up quite dramatically on sunny days and is not biodegradable. Emission of toxins is also widely discussed on social media, however significant changes have been made since the first artificial turf was introduced in the 1960s, with lead and crumb rubber free options now available. However cheap imports would appear to be best avoided. Moss lawns are also growing in popularity as an option, as are clover lawns which are more resistant to urine stains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this type of garden is to not only provide sensory interest, but also a place that is relaxing for your animal; and whatever space is available, sensory enrichment elements can be scaled up or down to fit within this area. &lt;a href=&quot;/services/enrichment/&quot;&gt;For more information about options to add see our Enrichment page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/sensory-gardens/dog-down.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dog staring down into camera&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companion animals can also benefit from having access to plants for their health and well-being, as well as for enrichment. These may be eaten, rolled in/rubbed against or just inhaled. In fact a study analysing wolf (the closest relative of the dog) scat during the summer months revealed their diet contained 8% grasses and berries, with other studies showing around 20% plant matter. It is sometimes thought grasses are consumed to prevent parasites, but David Mech (an American wolf expert) feels it may be consumed for the vitamin content. This is also backed up by RSPCA vet Dr Michael Lazaris who advises &amp;quot;Dogs eat grass to try and get vitamins missing from their food&amp;quot;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dogsfirst.ie/stage-1-grass-eater-trial-complete/&quot;&gt;A short study by Dogs First seems to support this, with only 1 in 10 of the dogs that regularly selected grass being diagnosed with worms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diet composition of wolves (Canis lupus) on the Scandinavian peninsula determined by scat analysis , S Muller&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some beneficial plants for dogs:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Barley grass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cat mint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chamomile (German)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleavers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Echinacea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fennel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lavender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon balm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemongrass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marshmallow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parsley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pot Marigold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wheatgrass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yarrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cats may too eat plant matter, but as this is indigestible for them it is unlikely to be for nutritional benefit. In a study of wild cat scat they found 25% contained plant matter, consisting mainly of grasses and twigs (Ref: Feeding Ecology of a Feral Cat Population on a Small Mediterranean Island).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some beneficial plants for cats:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Barley grass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Catnip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coriander&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lavender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon balm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peppermint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valerian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wheatgrass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbal supplements are sometimes added to an animal&#39;s feed however given the choice they may not choose all the constituents of these, but they could be broken down at a Herbal Choices session and offered individually; allowing your animal to choose. However, supplements prescribed by your vet should be continued and reviewed by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Holistichoundaoa&quot;&gt;For suitable seeds and organically grown plants have a look in our Shop on Etsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Wildlife Gardens</title>
    <link href="/services/wildlife-gardens/"/>
    <updated>2025-04-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>/services/wildlife-gardens/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Creating a wildlife garden&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introducing a range of habitats within a garden or urban space, such as yard or patio, not only provides a green urban network, but increases biodiversity and provides a range of food sources within the food webs, thus supporting nature. Invertebrates (insects), particularly Stag beetles and wood lice, can be encouraged by providing log piles (which may also be used by Queen bumblebees over winter), leaving fallen leaves and even standing plant pots on feet. Hedgehogs enjoy insects, eating beetles (around 30% of diet) and caterpillars (43%), along with the occasional slug (1%) and earthworms (8%). Grass lawns, rather than plastic, support burrowing insects and worms, and these provide a food source for birds, such as blackbirds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding a range of levels, such as different trees that grow to varying heights, hedging and dense bushes provide a range of habitats for different species, for instance Robins and Wrens prefer lower branches, whilst the Goldcrest prefers conifer trees. To ensure no nesting birds are disturbed, hedging should not be trimmed or cut from March until the end of the year (around November time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding flowering plants to these spaces supports pollinators, which includes bees, wasps, flies, hoverflies, beetles, moths and butterflies, with Hoverflies preferring compound/open flowers, while butterflies prefer bunched small tubular flowers. However, double petal flower varieties and annual bedding plants are best avoided, as they offer little value to pollinators. Plants provide both nectar, used as fuel and provides energy for flight, and pollen, which contains protein and carbohydrates, with many insects feeding on nectar, pollen, or both, while bees feed pollen to their larvae. Some plants support insects at different times of the day, for example honeysuckle supports moths at night, while some attract certain species such as Cinnibar moth caterpillar to Ragwort, and Peacock caterpillar to Nettles. Other plants, such as Ivy, provide food at different times of the year, the flowers support the early emerging pollinators, as well as berries for birds later in the year, while plants such as Teasels or Sunflowers could attract finches, in particular Goldfinches. Ladybirds also eat nectar and pollen as well as aphids, and as such are excellent at pest control. To provide nectar and pollen for as long as possible through the seasons it is worth considering, when planting, what flowers will be available at what time of year, and whether they are native plants. Another great pest controller is the earwig; these nocturnal insects keep pests at bay in orchards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ponds with at least one gently sloping edge not only provides habitat for reptiles such as toads, newts and frogs, but also an area for birds to bathe, and a water source for other animals such as hedgehogs. Adding plants to the pond itself can assist with oxygenation, whilst plants around its edge can provide cover and another habitat. If you have a water container in your garden always ensure there are a means to get out either by adding bricks or a ramp, or even a piece of string to allow insects to climb out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Blue Heart Campaign which was started in 2014 promotes rewilding in gardens (and along verges, in parks and school grounds), with a blue heart made from recycled materials placed in the area to highlight this. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bluecampaignhub.com/about-us&quot;&gt;For more information visit their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leaving an area within your garden to become a little overgrown or less managed it will not only increase the diversity of plants, but potentially lead to a wider range of insects, birds and possibly wild animals making use of this little haven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;case-img &quot; src=&quot;/static/images/blog/wildlife-gardens/butterfly-garden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;butterfly on a wild flower&quot; style=&quot;height: auto;&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our impact on nature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies have shown a decline in bees, birds and insects. In fact there has been a 57% reduction in farmland birds, and 27% reduction in woodland birds over the last 50 years, with some bird species showing a dramatic decline such as House Sparrows. In addition the organisation Plantlife reports that 97% of wildflower meadows have been lost since the 1930s, with a third of bumblebees and 70% of butterfly species in decline, and staggeringly it is estimated over 500 animal and plant species have become extinct over the last 200 years (Natural England). Some of these figures can be attributed to farming techniques, particularly in the use of pesticides and herbicides, and removal of habitat such as hedgerows and woodlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is however some good news, some species numbers have remained stable such as the Blue Tit and Wren, with others showing an increase such as the Nuthatch and Great spotted woodpecker. In addition there are also over 250 species of bees in the UK, including bumblebees, solitary and leaf cutter bees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully there is more awareness of the need for biodiversity, the definition of which is &amp;quot;variety of plant and animal life which is usually considered to be important and desirable&amp;quot;. A similar term is &amp;quot;rewilding&amp;quot; that upholds similar principles, but this is on a much larger scale and sees the restoration of ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are examples of projects with these principles in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://godneymarshes.com/&quot;&gt;Godney Marshes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambrianwildwood.org&quot;&gt;Cambrian Wildwood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with more projects here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rewildingbritain.org.uk/rewilding-network/projects&quot;&gt;Rewilding projects across Britain | Rewilding Britain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing predation by cats&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies conducted at the University of Exeter have found that playing with your cat around 5 - 10 minutes every day showed a 25% reduction in prey brought home. Additionally by feeding a meat rich diet, ideal for cats as they are obligate carnivores, this saw a 36% reduction in prey brought back. If your cat goes out with a collar (ideally a breakaway collar), then a bell could be added to alert wildlife of their presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ecosystem relies on the balance between plants and animals both in the food chain (known as trophic pyramids, that are sometimes referred to as pyramid of numbers), and food webs. Within these webs animals and birds usually rely on more than one species for food as this reduces the vulnerability of their own species. An example of a food web and our impact on it is the introduction of myxomatosis which reduced rabbits numbers, who were a food source for foxes. However foxes are adaptable and able to hunt other species, such as voles which is a food source for owls, and as such resulted in owl numbers dropping. Insects are at the base of the food chain and provide food for birds and bats and other animals that predate on them, such as hedgehogs. As such there is a predator-prey relationship and should there be a reduction in numbers of prey, whether it is plant matter, insects, or anything in the food chain, then predator numbers will ultimately be affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Organic gardening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When not using synthetic fertilizers, herbicides and pesticides this is usually referred to as organic gardening. By doing this you will not only be supporting an ecosystem that both sustains and nourishes plants and microbes, but your animals, insects, birds and wild animals that have access to your garden will also benefit. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworld.unu.edu/en/the-surprising-healing-qualities-of-dirt&quot;&gt;On a slightly different tangent could the soil itself be beneficial; particularly for our microbiome?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So what are the options?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One is the use of peat free compost, which can be purchased from a company called Yorganics. They quote on their website: &amp;quot;Yorganics is a 100% recycled, peat free, locally sourced and compost produced in North Yorkshire and West Yorkshire. Garden waste from households is recycled into a high quality compost that meets the British Standards Institution (BSI) PAS100 standard. It is ideal for both domestic, horticultural and agricultural uses.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yorganicscompost.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Use this postcode checker to find your local Yorganics stockist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why is it best to use peat free products?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazingly peat is actually created from the decaying remains of plants and &amp;quot;grows&amp;quot; about 1 mm a year. Peat bogs are also home to a host of plant and wildlife species that are only able to exist in this environment, with many bogs given the status of Sites of Special Scientific Interest (SSSI). Peat bogs also soak up water in upland areas which could reduce the risk of flooding. This is supported by a pilot study in Ceredigion (by the Wildlife Trust in Wales) which suggested up to 25% more water could be retained by properly managed bogs. It also acts as a carbon store. Pretty amazing stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How can I repel garden pests?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried copper tape around tubs and pots, but find this to be of little use in repelling snails and slugs. However, I have found sand, or small sharp stones, sprinkled on the soil around the plants helps significantly in repelling these pests, giving your seedlings a sporting chance! Due to its rough edges wood ash may also be useful as a repellent. For other pests, such as aphids, by encouraging insects into your garden, those that feed on these pests will eventually appear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We do not use any pesticides on our plants, all are organically grown.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/Holistichoundaoa&quot;&gt;Click here to see what seeds and plants we have available for a wildlife garden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
